Guide to the Society for the Prevention of Crime Records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Society for the Prevention of Crime Records,
1878-1973
Society for the Prevention of Crime (New York, N.Y.)
ca. 30,000 items (65 boxes, 8 oversize v. and folders)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079350
History
The Society for the Prevention of Crime was founded in 1877 in New York City. It has worked, successively, for the promotion of temperance, for judicial and legislative reform, and for public and legal education. During its most active periods, the Society brought about the formation of of the Lexow Committee to investigate the New York City Police in 1894, contributed to the Albany Crime Commission during the 1930s, and broadcast popular radio programs on criminal behavior, 1946-1948. In 1948 the Society absorbed the Vocational Foundation Bureau, a job placement agency for parolees. Since 1956, the Society's only activity has been its annual grant to Columbia Law School for research in penology.
Scope and Content
Papers of the Society, including correspondence among the officers and directors of the Society, memoranda, reports, legal papers, minutes, financial records, radio scripts, clippings, scrapbooks, comic books, and a subject file of pamphlets and clippings on all aspects of crime prevention. Also, an extensive history of the Society.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 2 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: General Files
Series III: Administration
Series IV: Eassay Contest
Series V: Financial
Series VI: Parkhurst, C. H. 1824-1933
Series VII: Publicity
Series VIII: Radio Programs
Series IX: Scrapbooks
Series X: Subjects
Series XI: Additional Information
Subjects
Albany Crime Commission (Albany, N.Y.); Columbia University.--School of Law.; Police--New York (State)--New York.; Crime prevention--Societies, etc.; Crime prevention--Citizen participation.; Temperance.; Social problems.; Corrections--Research.; Employment agencies.; Parole.; Scripts.; Scrapbooks.; Vocational Foundation Bureau.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-66. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1980 M-80 Society for the Preveition of Crime Gift
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Allen, Frederick Lewis (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, Roger Nash (Box 1)
  - Battle, George Gordon (Box 1)
  - Belmont, Eleanor Robson (Box 1)
  - Bernays, Edward L. (Box 1)
  - Biddle, Francis (Box 1)
  - Blanshard, Paul (Box 1)
  - Bliss, Cornelius Newton, Jr. (Box 1)
  - Braden, Spruille (Box 1)
  - Burlingham, Charles Culp (Box 1)
  - Caniff, Milton (Box 1)
  - Canner, Carl Lamson (Box 1)
  - Choate, Joseph Hodges, Jr. (Box 1)
  - Cortelyou, George Bruce (Box 1)
  - Crowther, Bosley (Box 1)
  - Damrosch, Walter (Box 1)
  - Davis, Noah (Box 1)
  - Dewey, Thomas Edward (Box 1)
  - du Pont, Pierre Samuel (Box 1)
  - Ellin, Stanley (Box 1)
  - Farrar, John Chipman (Box 1)
  - Field, Marshall (Box 1)
  - Finley, John Huston (Box 1)
  - Flagler, Harry Harkness (Box 1)
  - Fosdick, Harry Emerson (Box 1)
  - Harlan, John (Box 1)
  - Hogan, Frank Smithwick (Box 1)
  - Holmes, John Haynes (Box 1)
  - Holt, Hamilton (Box 1)
  - Hoover, John Edgar (Box 1)
  - Howe, Louis McHenry (Box 1)
  - Impellitteri, Vincent H. (Box 1)
  - Isaacs, Stanley Myer (Box 1)
  - Jerome, William Travers (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Alvin Saunders (Box 1)
  - Kinsey, Alfred Charles (Box 1)
  - Kirchwey, George Washington (Box 1)
  - La Guardia, Fiorello Henry (Box 1)
  - Lehman, Herbert Henry (Box 1)
  - Lewisohn, Sam A. (Box 1)
  - Lexow, Clarence (Box 1)
  - Lukas, Paul (Box 1)
  - McAneny, George (Box 1)
  - McCall, Edward Everett (Box 1)
  - McCay, Winsor Zenic (Box 1)
  - Mannes, Marya (Box 1)
  - Manning, William Thomas (Box 1)
  - Markel, Lester (Box 1)
  - Marshall, Margaret (Box 1)
  - Morgenthau, Henry (Box 1)
  - Moses, Robert (Box 1)
  - Odell, Benjsnin Barker (Box 1)
  - Parkhurst, Charles Henry (Box 1)
  - Parsons, Herbert (Box 1)
  - Prendergast, William A. (Box 1)
  - Pulitzer, Ralph (Box 1)
  - Riis, Jacob August (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller, John Davison, 3d. (Box 1)
  - Rustin, Bayard (Box 1)
  - Schieffelin, William Jay (Box 1)
  - Schwab, Charles M. (Box 1)
  - Shulman, Irving (Box 1)
  - Slicer, Thomas Roberts (Box 1)
  - Smith, Alfred Emanuel (Box 1)
  - Straus, Nathan (Box 1)
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Hays (Box 1)
  - Van Doren, Irita Bradford (Box 1)
  - Wald, Lillian D. (Box 1)
  - White, Horace (Box 1)
- Series II: General Files
  - Letters to Frank Moss, 1890-1902 -- Correspondence between Samuel Marcus and Howard Clark Barker, and others, 1913-1920 -- Correspondence of Howard M. Bassett, George Drew Egbert, George F. Hammond, Henry N. Pringle, Samuel Marcus, Harry Sussman and others; reports, clippings, etc., 1923-1940 -- Correspondence of Paul Bianshard, Benjamin M. Day, Edwin J. Lukas, and others; reports, press releases, etc., 1941-1950 (Box 2-5)
  - File of Bernhard K. Schaefer: corresrondence, reports, accounts, etc. (including the Vocational Foundation Bureau and "A history of the Society for the Prevention of Crime." [1969] by Paul W. Rishell & Albert E. Roraback, 113 (Box 6 - 9)
- Series III: Administration
  - Annual reports, 1920-1949 (Box 10)
  - Board of Directors; Board of Trustees. Correspondence, 1937-1953 (Box 10)
  - Certificate of incorporation - typescript copies (Box 11)
  - Committees, 1946-1951 (Box 11)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1923-1942 (Box 11)
  - Dexter bequest - correspondence, 1914-1936 (Box 11)
    [Henry Dexter, 1813-1910, philanthropist and President of the American News Company, made a bequest to the Society in his will which was contested on behalf of his daughter - legal papers, 1910-1936]
  - Dexter bequest - printed legal briefs and other documents, 1910--1936 (Box 12)
  - Executive Committee, 1945-1951 (Box 12)
  - Expansion plans, 1941-1949 (Box 12)
  - Minutes, 1909-1934 (Box 13)
  - Minutes, 1924-1952 (Box 14)
  - Minutes, 1942-1952 (Box 15)
  - Minutes - The City Vigilance League of New York -- --Board of Trustees -- --Executive Committee -- --General Committee, 1895-1898 (Box 16)
  - Plan and Scope Committee, 1933-1941 (Box 17)
  - Staff applications, 1937-1950 (Box 17)
  - Whitney, David J. Memorial Volume, 1892 (Box Oversize no. 6)
- Series IV: Eassay Contest
  - "The best program of practicable steps to reduce law-breaking in New York City", 1926 (Box 17)
- Series V: Financial
  - Account books, 1877-1946 (Box 18)
  - Account book, 1935-1941 (Box Oversize no. 2)
  - Account book, 193l-19 -- Accounts, 1922-1935 -- Auditor's reports, 1912-1954 (Box 19)
  - Banks, 1941-1954 -- Budget, 1951 -- Insurance record, 1935-1939 -- Investment Committee, 1925-1953 -- --Green, Ellis & Anderson, 1936-1945 -- --J. & W. Seligman & Co., 1943-1953 -- Receipts, 1938-1940 -- S.P.C.. Holding Company, 1905-1953 -- Stock certificates (blank book), 1932 -- Taxes, 1936-1955 -- Treasurer's reports, 1946-1954 -- Misc., l928-1944 (Box 20)
- Series VI: Parkhurst, C. H. 1824-1933
  Pastor of the Madison Square Presbyterian Church, was President of the Society from 1891 to 1908 and a leader in the reform movement in New York City politics. A memorial to him was proposed for Madison Square but was never built
  - Parkhurst Testimonial, 1894 (Box 21)
  - Parkhurst Luncheon, 1922 (Box 21)
  - Parkhurst Memorial - correspondence, reports, clippings, photos, etc., 1928-1936 (Box 21)
  - Parkhurst Memorial - correspondence, etc., 1935-1941 (Box 22)
  - The New Yorker articles on Parkhurst, 1955 (Box 22)
- Series VII: Publicity
  - Fund raising, 1940-1951 (Box 22)
  - Projects, 1945-1949 (Box 22)
  - Radio promotions, 1948-1950 (Box 22)
  - Releases, l943-1949 (Box 22)
- Series VIII: Radio Programs
  - Crime--causes and prevention, 12 September 1946 (Box 23)
  - Criminal casebook, 1948 (Box 23)
  - American Broadcasting Company, 1945-1949 (Box 23)
  - Convict releases, 1945-1949 (Box 23)
  - Critical comments, 1945-1949 (Box 23)
  - Criminal casebook -- --Prospects -- --Publicity -- --Requests for aid -- --Scripts 1-10 & 13 -- --Sources - criminal & paychiatrist, 1948 (Box 24)
  - I was a convict -- --Correspondence with convicts, releases, case histories, scripts, etc.; A - G, 1945-1949 (Box 25)
  - I was a convict: Correspondence, etc.: H (Box 26)
  - I was a convict: -- --Correspondence, etc.: P - W -- --Maxwell, Robert, Associates (Producer) -- --Miscellaneous -- --Publicity -- --Receipts -- --Scripts, Jan. - March 1946 & [n.d.] (Box 27)
  - I was a convict -- --Scripts: April 1946 - June 1947 -- --Sponsors (Box 28)
- Series IX: Scrapbooks
  - Compiled by Edwin Jay Lukas, 1888-1948 (Box Oversize no. 3)
  - Compiled by Edwin Jay Lukas, 1941-1947 (Box Oversize no. 4)
  - Compiled by Edwin Jay Lukas, 1947-1950 (Box Oversize no. 5)
- Series X: Subjects
  - Acceptance of offenders by the armed forces, 1940-1942 (Box 29)
  - Adolescent girls, 1939-1947 (Box 29)
  - Adolescent treatment clinic, 1941-1948 (Box 29)
  - Alcoholism, 1938-1950 (Box 29)
  - Alien enemy material, 1941-1942 (Box 29)
  - Armed forces. See: Acceptance of offenders by the armed forces (Box 29)
  - Armed services criminality, 1944-1946 (Box 29)
  - Albany Crime Conference, 1931-1938 (Box 30)
  - Behavior problems & children's institutions, 1946-1950 (Box 31)
  - Bail, 1941 (Box 31)
  - Bibliographies, 1944-1951 (Box 31)
  - Brownsville Boys Club, 1943-1949 (Box 31)
  - Capital punishment. See: Murderers & capital punishment Cartoons (Box 32)
  - Cartoons (Box Oversize no. 7)
  - Cases; A - R, 1896-1951 (Box 32)
  - Cases: S - Y & misc., 1932-1950 (Box 33)
  - Child adoption legislation, 1939-1951 (Box 34)
  - Child labor, 1942-1949 (Box 35)
  - Children. See: Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children (Box 35)
  - Children. See; War & children (Box 35)
  - Children's Court, 1938-1949 (Box 35)
  - Children's institutions. See: Behavior problems & children's Inst. (Box 35)
  - Civil Service, 1941-1944 (Box 35)
  - Civil rights, 1949 (Box 35)
  - Civil rights. See also: Race (Box 35)
  - Comic books. See: Motion pictures, magazines (Box 35)
  - Correction & penal institutions (1), 1932-1945 (Box 35)
  - Correction & penal institutions (2), 1946-1950 (Box 36)
  - Court interpretations. See: Legislation & court interpretations (Box 36)
  - Courts, 1941-1951 (Box 36)
  - Courts. See: Children's Court (Box 36)
  - Courts. See: Youth Court (Box 36)
  - Courts; Brooklyn County Clerk's Office - annual report (County Court), 1940 (Box 36)
  - Crime & delinquency, 1932-1951 (Box 37)
  - Crime & delinquency: other countries, 1933-l949 (Box 37)
  - Crime causation. See: Popular concepts of crime causation (Box 37)
  - Crime statistics. See; Delinquency & crime statistics (Box 37)
  - Criminology, 1934-1949 (Box 37)
  - Delinquency. See; Crime & delinquency (Box 37)
  - Delinquency & crime statistics, l939-l946 (Box 37)
  - Delinquency & crime statistics (2), 1947-1951 (Box 39)
  - Delinquency, unofficial (non-statistical), 1943 (Box 40)
  - Detention, l939-1950 (Box 40)
  - Detention facilities (1), 1938-1946 (Box 41)
  - Detention facilities (2), 1947-1951 (Box 42)
  - Drugs, 1936-1939 (Box 42)
  - Education (1), 1938-1944 (Box 42)
  - Education (2), 1945-1950 (Box 43)
  - Egbert, George Drew Sermons, 1935-1936 (Box 44)
    [G.D. Egbert was President of the Society from 1933 to 1940 and Pastor of the First Congergational Church, Flushing, NY]
  - Foster home care, 1946-1949 (Box 44)
  - Foundations, 1943 (Box 44)
  - Gambling (1), 1906-1934 (Box 44)
  - Gambling (2), 1935-1955 (Box 45)
  - Gang activities, 1943-1951 (Box 45)
  - Government, 1931-1939 (Box 46)
  - Guidance clinics, 1949 (Box 46)
  - Health, 1943-1949 (Box 47)
  - Housing, 1937-1950 (Box 47)
  - Legislation & court interpretations, 1941-1951 (Box 48)
  - Lexow Committee: Minutes, Vol. 2 & Vol. 1 -- -- "Investigations of the Police Department and other departments of the city of New York by a committee of the Senate; 1894; Vol. II; Frank Moss of Counsel for Committee" -- -- "Lexow Committee's original minutes; Vol. IV; 1894" (Box 49)
  - Marriage and divorce, 1947-1950 (Box 50)
  - Mental deficiency, 1938-1950 (Box 50)
  - Miscellaneous, 1901-1950 (Box 50)
  - Motion pictures, magazines, radio, comics in relation to delinquency (includes many comic books), 1938-1948 (Box 50)
  - Motion pictures, magazines, radio, comics ... (2), 1947 & 1948 (Box 51)
  - Motion pictures, magazines, radio, comics (3) (includes the censorship trial of The Amboy Dukes by Irving Shuinan), 1949-1950 (Box 52)
  - Murderers & capital punishment, 1939-1949 (Box 52)
  - Narcotics, 1938-1951 (Box 52)
  - New York City. Juvenile Aid Bureau. See: "Politics and children" (Box 52)
  - New York State. See: Albany Crime Conference (Box 52)
  - New York State. Legislature. Senate. Committee on the Police Department of the city of New York. See: Lexow Committee (Box 52)
  - Pari-mutual legislation, l938-1940 (Box 52)
  - Parole. See: Probation & parole (Box 52)
  - Parolees. See: Problems of prisoners & parolees (Box 52)
  - Penal institutions. See: Correction & penal institutions (Box 52)
  - Planned parenthood, 1941-1946 (Box 52)
  - Police, 1945-1951 (Box 53)
  - Police. See also: Lexow Committee "Police and children" -a study of New York City's Juvenile Aid Bureau, 1949 (Box 53)
  - Popular concepts of crime causation, 1946-1949 (Box 53)
  - Population statistics, 1939-1948 (Box 53)
  - Post war planning, 1942-1951 (Box 53)
  - Preventive measures, 1942-1951 (Box 54)
  - Probation & parole, 1936-1951 (Box 55)
  - Problems of prisoners & parolees, 1942-1949 (Box 55)
  - Prostitution, 1923-1951 (Box 56)
  - Psychiatric cases & notes (1), 1928-1945 (Box 57)
  - Psychiatric cases & notes (2), 1946-1950 (Box 58)
  - Race discrimination amendment, 1944-1950 (Box 59)
  - Race prejudice (l), 1941-1947 (Box 59)
  - Race prejudice (2), 1948-1950 (Box 60)
  - Race prejudice. See also: Civil rights (Box 60)
  - Rackets, 1933 (Box 60)
  - Radio, 1944-1948 (Box 60)
  - Radio. See also: Motion pictures, magazines, radio (Box 60)
  - Recreation & nursery care, 1940-1949 (Box 61)
  - Religion, 1940-1949 (Box 61)
  - Sex education, 1943-1949 (Box 61)
  - Sex offenders (1), 1935-1946 (Box 61)
  - Sex offenders (2), l947-1950 (Box 62)
  - Shulman, Irving The Amboy Dukes See: Motion pictures (Box 62)
  - Social action, 1941-1950 (Box 62)
  - Social work (1), 1935-1947 (Box 62)
  - Social work (2), 1948-1949 (Box 63)
  - Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, 1900-1942 (Box 63)
  - Treatment programs, 1939-1951 (Box 63)
  - Venereal disease, l939-l948 (Box 63)
  - Vocational education, 1935-1948 (Box 64)
  - War & children, 1942-1944 (Box 64)
  - War criminals, 1942-1949 (Box 64)
  - Welfare societies, 1937 & 1938 (Box 64)
  - Youth, 1940-1949 (Box 64)
  - Youth correction authority, 1940-1949 (Box 65)
  - Youth Court (1), 1919-1941 (Box 65)
  - Youth Court (2), 1942-1951 (Box 66)
- Series XI: Additional Information
  - Original order of the subject headings: -- -- 1. Crime & delinquency - general -- 2. Crime & delinquency - other countries -- 3. War criminals -- 4. Armed services criminality -- 5. Murderers & capital punishment -- 6. Gang activities -- 7. Adolescent girls -- 8. Prostitution -- 9. Sex deviates (sex offenders) -- 10. Alien enemy material -- 11. Gambling -- 12. War & children -- 12-A. Youth -- 12-B. Child labor -- 13. Unofficial delinquency -- 14. Narcotics -- 15. Alcoholism -- 16. Health -- 17. Venereal disease -- 18. Mental defficiency -- 19. Motion pictures, magazines, radio, comics in relation to delinquency -- 20. Race prejudice -- 21. Race discrimination amendment -- 22. Religion -- 23. Preventive measures -- 24. Treatment programs -- 25. Education -- 26. Sex education -- 27. Vocational education -- 28 Planned parenthood -- 29. Recreation & nursery care -- 30. Housing -- 31. Social work -- 32. Foster home care -- 33. Radio -- 34. Foundations -- 35. Post war planning -- 36. Youth correction authority -- 37. Courts -- 38. Youth Court -- 39. Children's Court -- 40. -- 41. Correctional & penal institutions -- 42. Detention -- 43. Detention facilities -- 44. Probation & parole -- 45. Problems of prisioners & parolees -- 46. Behavior problems & children's institutions -- 47. Bail -- 48. Criminology - general -- 49. Psychiatric cases & notes -- 50. Civil Service -- 51. Population statistics -- 52. Delinquency & crime statistics -- 53. Popular concepts of crime causation -- 54. Police -- 55. Social action -- 56. Civil rights -- 57. Marriage and divorce -- 58. Miscellaneous -- 59. Guidance clinics Some officers of the Societry who appear in the correspondence: -- Frank Moss [Counsel 1887-1908; President 1908-1909] -- Charles Henry Parkhurst [President 1891-1908] -- Samuel Marcus [Counsel 1908-1936] -- Charles E. Bruce [President 1909-1921] -- S. Edward Young [President 1921-1927] -- Howard Clark Barber [Superintendent -1932; Director 1925-1932, 1936-1939] -- William Jay Schieffelin [President 1927-1933] -- Albert E. Roraback [Vice-Presdident 1926-] -- Howard M. Bassett -- George P. Hammond [Superintendent 1932-1935] -- George Drew Egbert [President 1933-1940] -- Henry N. Pringle [Investihator; Superintentent] -- Harry Sussman [Investigator] -- Lionel J. Freeman [Superintendent 1935-1937] -- J. Edward Lumbard [Counsel 1937-] -- Benjamin M. Day [President 1940-1942] -- Paul Blanshard [Ex Secretary 1941/1942] -- George H. Sibley President 1942-1948] -- Edwin Jay Lukas [Ex Secretary 1943-1950; Ex Director 1950] -- Clarence O. Dimmock [Counsel 1943-] -- Bernhard K. Schaefer [President 1948-] -- K. Brent Woodruff [Ex Director, 1950/1951] (Box 1)